welcome back everyone I'm dr. Andy
Calvin and this is 25 minute physiology
today we're talking all things endurance
conditioning fatigue whatever label you
want to put on now in previous videos
some five-minute and some 55 minute
Biggers we've talked about all these
difference these six different points
you're seeing on the screen alright so
in this particular video though we're
gonna talk about number one and lelee
number two which is how to design your
programs your workouts or your training
whatever you want to call it to optimize
or improve your endurance now before we
do that I have to define you what I mean
by endurance and I like to put them into
a couple of different categories all
right so that's we're gonna get into
today thanks for sticking around and
let's have some fun so you can see the
actual definition of endurance down
there it doesn't particularly matter in
my mind it's anything that makes you
tired and there's a bunch of different
versions of that so I like to put them
in three broad categories the first
being muscular endurance and high
intensity and in long duration endurance
and you can see a quick example on the
screen and I'll go through each one of
these in more detail now the reality of
it is I actually split high intensity up
into multiple different categories and
you could split these up into Infinite
different ones it just depends on how
specific or detail do you want to be so
if you come from a background where you
actually like to categorize them
slightly different it doesn't
particularly matter if that's the case I
would actually strongly encourage you to
watch the long 55 minute physiology of
endurance video because in that I
actually show how I don't really think
about endurance training like this I
think about the physiological problem or
the limiting factor performance and I
program around that but if that didn't
make any sense to you at all start with
this particular video even if that
didn't make sense you you could probably
gain a couple of things from this I
almost guarantee you when we get to the
muscular endurance I can bring some
things up that you're probably not doing
very often in your training or
specifically sorry in the high-intensity
stuff right a lot of people are doing
high intensity intervals but there's a
lot of mistakes are being made in that
realm okay so a quick example the
muscular endurance is it's several
repetitions that you can see my friend
Chris Moore here in the picture
and he's attempting to lift that car as
many times as he possibly can so that's
a muscular endurance fact he's going to
be limited by the endurance and muscle
the actual local exercising muscle he
won't be limited by his cardiovascular
system or his pulmonary system or his
blood flow or anything like that high
intensity is a little bit different
now you're talking more like circuit
training you can see coach McKee there
Alex and CPT doing that circuit and
things like that do you all know
different examples of high-intensity
interval training and that's gonna be
limited by things that are different not
necessarily always just to the
exercising muscle itself it could now
start working in the systemic
difficulties and then at the other end
of the spectrum Amelia their long
duration during stuff not limited by
muscular endurance good example here a
one-mile run is not muscular endurance
that's slightly different right a long
duration endurance in my mind is when
you're covering big distances are big
time intervals fairly consistently there
could be small intervals within them
like you would see in a Spartan Race or
something like that but the entire
duration is is his longer ride his it's
a much much more extended so to go into
each one of them a little more detail
there
muskan endurance in my mind is how many
times you can do given a certain
activity a certain amount of times so
this typically ends up being medium to
low percentage of your one-arm max this
is one of the two technical ways we can
define intensity so intensity either
based on percentage of your vo2 Max or
your heart rate or in this particular
case percentage of your 1-room axis so
because you're doing muscular endurance
multiple times it ends up having to be
medium to low muscular endurance would
not be something like I did 95% for two
took a break I did that a whole bunch of
times that is a special type of strength
endurance which is a little bit
different so for now I think muscular
endurance is the classic how many
pushups can you do in a minute something
like this how that's different from high
intensity is those can be at medium to
high percentages of you're wondering max
but typically we differentiate this here
and we talk about this as being a
percentage of your vo2 Max or your heart
rate so it's no longer about the weight
per se where the muscular is typically
is now we're talking cardiovascular
pulmonary challenge so typically
it can't be high weight can be low it
really kind of depends long duration of
course is low to very low oftentimes sub
body weight ie swimming right you're
actually moving less than your body
weight cycling rowing things like that
right now don't be confused here I'm not
saying any one of these is less
difficult or more difficult than another
more awesome or fatiguing anything like
that they're just percentage of low
higher low percentages of your one right
max so how I want to get into this video
and the way I like to teach is to teach
two things concepts and methods if you
hit the proper concepts I'm getting at
here the methods can be almost limitless
and so I will give you some methods as
examples but I really want to get to the
concepts and that's what I'll spending
the most amount of time on so let's jump
into some of these concepts the first
one we're gonna talk about is that
muscular endurance so some basic
concepts here this can be programmed in
terms of the choice of exercise via
single or easy small movement exercises
or multi-joint complex movements either
one example a single joint movement you
can do muscular endurance of your
triceps no problem if for whatever
reason you've decided that's an issue
you need to work on you can do single
leg hamstring or it could be abdominal
muscle endurance or you could pick
complex exercises burpees lunges twists
jumps whatever they happen to be alright
so either one of these is fine in terms
of choosing the exercise no problem
you're going to want to typically do
somewhere between three to five ish sets
abut this of course I say issue because
it really depends on the athlete the the
goal a training cycle what type of
movements you're doing when you're doing
tomorrow yesterday etc but typically 3
to 5 is a very standard place to start
now it's going to happen somewhere
between the 12 to 100 repetitions per
set range but it's mostly like the 12 to
25 ish okay if we start talking past
that now you're probably moving into a
position where you're no longer being
limited by the actual local muscle and
again it's more of a pulmonary
cardiovascular blood issue and also
happens to typically be very liked
because of that and so this is where the
is the key thing to differentiate
muscular endurance is it's some
repetition range 30 40 50 reps again the
key example here how many pushups can
you do in a minute around 30 40 60 80
something it's not 3000 it will never be
right it's gonna be limited by that it's
not also 5 that's gonna be limited by
strength not the endurance of the muscle
per se right and there's some great
areas absolutely I give you ish
told it 100 it right so there's a lot of
grain there but that's typically what
we're talking about for muscular
endurance so because of that it has a
pretty wide range of the percent
intensity you can use a might be pretty
damn high it's really tough to do 12
repetitions or more than 80% but it is
possible some people can do it I have an
its terror its absolute terror but
mostly you're talking 50 60 % at most of
your of your maximum you're going to
want to take somewhere between 3 or 30
seconds and 180 seconds of rest in
between your set but again this really
really depends you can go a little bit
shorter just don't compromise the
intensity of the rep range you have some
wiggle room on those things so fast or
slow speed so these could be things like
again as many pushups as you can do in a
minute and you're gonna crank those out
as fast as you can but at some duration
half way in or something you're gonna
really slow down or it could be in tenth
place long there's no reason you can't
work on muscular endurance by doing
really slow repetitions and you might
want to get 5 reps in a minute or you
might do something like isometric for
that matter it could be a wall sit and
you're trying to hold a wall sit for 40
seconds if that's tough for a plank
position a plank is a muscular endurance
task very good way to think of it some
people can only hold a side plank sake
for 30 seconds not to challenge that's a
very slow movement so examples of
methods I've already described a couple
sprints are ok here but not typically a
great example of muscular endurance it's
led push a sled do some rowing any of
the extra other exercises I mentioned
repetitions to failure is a great scheme
if you've ever done that right so you
said extra loading you don't even have a
rep range you're hitting it's as many as
you can until the muscle fails fantastic
concept circuits can be good there just
be careful we don't go into other
reigns of training
but if you did something like you know
20 bodyweight squats and 20 push-ups and
20 pull-ups and that's gonna work on
muscular endurance assuming you don't do
it for a very very long time there's a
touch of it there as I mentioned
isometrics where you're not moving at
all holding a position so you could hold
a bicep curl hold a half squat hold a
lunge hold the wall squat hold the plank
hold an overhead press or push-up
position whatever you want to be
virtually anything here that you want
that you can do maximally without a huge
eccentric load and this is the thing
that's very very important for all of
our endurance fatigue or conditioning
training and it's very different and say
our strength speed power or even
hypertrophy training with endurance we
typically want to be very careful we
want to minimize the amount of eccentric
loading this is because that type of
training or that type of muscular
contraction causes a lot more muscular
damage it doesn't mean you can't do it
just means you need to be very aware and
conscious of how you implement these
things a good example if you have an
athlete who are an individual who's not
extremely trained or hasn't done any
eccentric stuff in a long time and you
have them do even three or four or five
reps of eccentric say squatting or
jumping jumping is a good one right you
have to eat absorb the land it's not the
jump off that that is a problem
it's the eccentric load when you land
well if somebody hasn't jumped in 15
years and you have them do three sets of
five jumps then probably the walk that
wake up tomorrow extremely sore now
imagine you have them do that for a
circuit three or four rounds of sets of
twenty they're gonna be brutalized the
next day you're gonna be absolutely
train wreck for weeks at a time
especially an athlete you might be gone
for three four or five days a week
a non-athlete that might be several
weeks and so it's a real big problem I'm
not saying at all you can't do these I'm
just saying you have to really
understand when you start implementing
eccentric exercises or movements for a
whole bunch of repetitions I'm real real
real real real problem you can you can
take advantage of easing the eccentric
load and this is something like a box
squat okay so if you jump and land on a
box the amount of eccentric loading is
severely minimized now I'm still not a
huge fan of you
box squats for most of endurance for
most people if you're in a sport or an
activity which requires that fine but
the risk reward ratio is pretty in for
box jumps for conditioning purposes but
that's one thing that can be possible
notice with rowing and dragging a sled
all those things have very minimal
eccentric action its push push push it's
not a land absorb if you run often
running a spine if you don't run often
and this is gonna be a real big problem
especially if you do some like agility
work and you try to do an agility
circuit for conditioning and it evolves
a lot of stopping and going back the
other way that's a really big e
eccentric load and that's gonna be a
problem
all right so just be very very very
careful isometric seem to be just fine
concentric is just fine a little
eccentric okay a whole bunch of
eccentric it's a real big problem
alright so again to recap not against it
just make sure you really think through
who you're giving it to and what amounts
and they prepared for it do they move
well in those positions etc and because
of this I typically am going to
recommend for all of these training
modalities in the endurance realm very
little if any implementation of weight
lifting movements and by weight lifting
I mean very specifically Olympic weight
lifting so no snatches or clean and
jerks or no variations of those no power
jerks no power cleans now hang cleans
for more than twelve or so repetitions
now even after eight repetitions it gets
sort of questionable if you work in a
facility or environment that does this
and you're trained then you move well
and this is a normal party or routine no
problem it can certainly be done I know
plenty of people I do very high
repetition I want the coiler thing
movements no issue I typically though as
a general statement don't think it's a
good risk reward
same thing with plyometrics think of
plyometrics is jumping and landing
alright so leaping bounding all this
stuff you just have to be very careful
because of what the playas that you
centric component and with the weight
lifting movements again you're the whole
point of muscular endurance
high-intensity stuff for long duration
is induce fatigue and so now you're
asking an athlete to go overhead or an
individual to get in a compromised
position
ready with extreme fatigue can certainly
be done again don't misinterpret there
but let's just think about it my
personal philosophy is unless you're
working with individuals that does that
or needs to do that in the competition
there's probably other ways we can
achieve our endurance without those
particular moments so again just think
okay use your best judgment with who
you're using and with are they prepared
or the pros and cons sort of the risk
reward to those things now what you'll
notice here is for the high intensity
I'm actually going to split it up into
two separate categories okay
category one with high intensity is what
I call an aerobic endurance so a in this
is not I repeat is not something like
your max power so we talked about your
maximal anaerobic capacity or your
maximal aerobic endurance I'm not
talking about your max sprint speed or
your max clean jerk we're talking about
a fatigue issue right so if we're
talking maximal an aerobic endurance
remember it's in still an endurance
issue so something has to be taken to
fatigue but it's the anaerobic side of
the equation this is almost exclusively
with complex movements I don't know if
I've ever seen anybody do in an aerobic
endurance bout with the single joint
exercise or bicep curl or something like
that again three to 12 ish sense really
depends on all the stuff we've talked
about but this is what differentiates
them I no longer at this point program
or repetition ranges because it doesn't
really make sense this is better thought
of as they work to rest ratio and I
think it's just swinging anywhere from
like a 1 to sorry like a three to one
work to rest all the way to a 1 to fine
now most of you I'm sure have done
something like this and you probably
have done the classic 20 on 15 off or 30
on 30 off sprint the straightaways walk
the corner type of thing right yeah done
this yeah I'm sure it's awesome well
most people tend to stick to that 1 to 1
work to rest ratio but the total
duration is very short this is what
makes it an aerobic conditioning so you
can't do an aerobic endurance work or
conditioning work for more than say 2 or
3 minutes of a individual go without
taking a break
if you do it longer than that that's
that's a separate endurance thing which
we'll talk about just a second okay but
what most people fail to do is
manipulate that work to rest range you
arrange a ratio very often so a three to
one would be something like thirty
seconds as hard as you can
but now ten seconds off oh it's brutal
but everything has a pro and a con okay
if we go the other end of the spectrum
like a one two three this would be the
same thirty seconds of work but now
you're taking 90 seconds of rest alright
so the time domain doesn't matter it's
the ratio or you can go about the one to
five so ten seconds to work fifty
seconds off whatever well these two
different types of an aerobic
conditioning give you very different
adaptation if you keep a very high work
a very low rest ratio the quality of the
next round goes down right you imagine
thirty seconds as hard as you can on a
bike on with those upper body lower body
bikes right and you get ten seconds off
you're not even close to recover for the
next thirty seconds
what that does is help you train at
trying to work through extreme fatigue
you're not going to get an improved
performance there because you're just
gonna survive and that's good but the
downside is not gonna enhance peak
performance right the other in the
spectrum which is now say twenty seconds
of work and a minute and a half rest
well the accumulated fatigue from that
twenty seconds to work is going to be
long dissipated in that one hundred
fifty seconds and so you're gonna be
able to train yourself to work up to a
higher peak again not twenty seconds
you're gonna be really putting out doing
power outputs are covering far distance
or doing a lot of good work so if you
need to practice increasing the work you
can get done in a short time demand gave
yourself more rest it's still plenty
fatiguing and it's actually fatiguing in
a different way because the work you do
in that same say twenty second interval
is so much more than the work you do in
the other twenty second interval when
you only had ten seconds of rest I don't
give you tangible number imagine you're
going on a rower and I'll make a number
up and then make sense at all but it'll
help you if you've never wrote maybe in
twenty seconds you can make it a hundred
meters and then when I give you ten
seconds to rest the next time you go for
that twenty seconds instead of getting a
hundred meters you go ninety and the
next time it's more like 50
and you just fall off the earth right
you just tank and you're just barely
moving by the third fourth fifth round
well the other way where I give you that
20 seconds - oh man you get a hundred
and they give you min and a half off
next time you go again you might be 97
you might be back at 100 you might be
able to stay at 100 three four five six
rounds in or by the seventh eighth round
you might be down to 95 or fifth round
or whatever happens to be and so now the
fourth round of the first style you're
doing half the amount of distance but
the fourth round of the other style you
maybe 97% of your Mac systems the
downside of that set the style though
with the long rest intervals you're not
necessarily working on recovery
right not necessarily working on dealing
with a really high fatigue level right
and so both of them have their place but
they're still both gonna help you with
their maximal an aerobic endurance
so my recommendation your homework if
you will is if you do intervals well
first of all if you don't do intervals
mm-hmm shame on you
and angry professor face here but when
you do them change it change your work
pace a little bit change the narration
if you always do 30 seconds go to 45 all
45 5 is a mother oh it's a breaking
point right or go 10 seconds you've
always done 30 you've always done 30
you've really done 45 60 seconds go 15
second goes and really push the power
output almost 50 second goes it's it's
gonna be different than the metabolic
demands are actually slightly different
the energy in the physiology is
different okay but regardless whatever
you're doing whatever work to rest ratio
you use for an aerobic conditioning or
an aerobic endurance it's gonna have to
be by definition greater than your vo2
Max and this is normal physiology you'll
have to read up on vo2 max if that
confuses you but not grating your
heartrate max heart rate of course but
grading your vo2 max which means it's
anaerobic and you're gonna maximize
speed on all your repetitions throughout
but depending on your work rest ratio
you may in fact slow down quite a bit in
terms of the method you use same kind of
idea that we talked about muscular
endurance Sprint's are great here now
fantastic uphill Sprint's are great
sleds rowing all all amazing anything
you can do maximum without a huge e
centric opponent because again the rep
range gets very very very high if you
want to integrate some weightlifting
apply into this
little bit okay but just be careful so
now that we understand an aerobic
conditioning let's move on to a robic
condition and we're robic endurance and
did you see the slide change or any aha
gotcha you were sleeping on don't sleep
no sleep I caught you
loop's on Kurama no sleeping okay my
flashback anaerobic aerobic anaerobic
aerobic you notice the subtle difference
here same basically identical but with a
difference in work to rest the major
difference between anaerobic and aerobic
is the time domain so you can still do
the inner low so you can still be 1 to 1
or 2 to 1 or 1 to 2 or something like
that but now instead of this being 2 or
3 minutes at the maximum you're probably
looking at 3 to 15 minutes or so per
round a very classic track and field's
across country example are called 1 mile
repeats if you've never done them you
have some other homework to do they're
fantastic you can do the same thing on a
bike or a row and just make the
equivalent change in distance but
something that takes you seven eight
minutes six minutes somewhere in that
range however long it takes you to take
that exact amount or at rest and do it
again it's a one-to-one ratio right you
can do slightly different you could do a
you know a five minute
whatever how fast most differences you
can cover in five minutes take five
minutes software to peek down and take
ten minutes off maybe one to two right
oh that's a fantastic workout a little
long Brian Mackenzie power speed
endurance his book is fantastic and
describes how you can use this style of
training to accomplish the models you
need to accomplish to do something like
a marathon so I'm just jogging for 10
straight miles do something why are you
do 800 meter repeats and accumulate
seven miles much more effective way of
training for a lot of reasons
I shouldn't say more effective but it's
repower speed endurance okay very very
very good follow that that website and
so this is maximal anaerobic condition
the difference here now is it is
something that takes you at some point
in the finale to your vo2 max ish you
can also think of this as maximum heart
rate pretty close but
maximal aerobic endurance is your
ability to get up to that maximal
aerobic endurance which is our
definition basically a vo2 max it is not
long duration endurance maximal aerobic
capacity is not your ability to jog for
30 minutes it is how much work can you
do in that 8 to 12 15 minute time domain
that's it so play with your numbers here
do three minutes on one minute off
repeat eight-minute on 16 off you get it
right give you some different examples
of there and of course choose whatever
method you like so if we combine those
two together in my 351 class I typically
think about this kind of just talk about
muscular endurance high intensity and
long duration so I combined the
anaerobic and aerobic into high
intensity right so what you're seeing
here for high intensity is kind of a
combination at an aerobic anaerobic so
end up being work the rest ratios there
the rep ranges are kind of goofy and
things kind of combined over there right
so I gave you some other examples one
Maori piece walk jogs etc etc all right
so now let's finish up this whole
25-minute series I think we're getting
pretty close to that 25-minute
time-domain depending on how close ya
and finish up with long duration in
turns this is by definition typically
one set or one repetition it is
continuous there can be slight
undulations right change tempo a little
bit go up and down but it's it's roughly
continuous so I'd doesn't have to be
literally steady state it's some maximum
because you're doing it for a long
duration of time and now we're talking
anything typically longer than 12 to 15
minutes as I mentioned before there's
huge great area with all this don't get
too bogged up and while he was 11:59 so
then yeah just think about it more
conceptually major difference here being
you want to emphasize low speeds and
typically efficiency because the goal of
long duration endurance is not
necessarily time to completion it's
distance traveled or time to work right
so a good example here makes me involved
in an undergraduate class where it was
called a marathon class and so you
signed up the first day you ran as far
as you could
most people made it five miles or so and
in order to get an A in the class at the
end you had to run a complete marathon
now didn't matter that you improved your
time your speed or anything like that it
just you had to be able to travel for
their distance without breaking down a
stopping and by the end of the class
almost every person completed the entire
26 miles vo2 max it didn't change all
right their vo2 max did not go up at all
they just improved their ability to
cover a long distance and that's
important that's good that's healthy I
like it too that's crazy it's impressive
it's difficult it's fun but that is not
necessarily directly improving your vo2
max or your maximal aerobic endurance
just improving your ability to do more
continuous work so that's how I like to
break these things up obstacle course
racing cycling all the stuff physical
activity can be long duration work
gardening working whatever it's cetera
or anything you can do maximally or that
time limit so that being said that wraps
up point number one and two if you want
to hear more about why we get tired how
we make cellular energy what is that vo2
max exactly and why we breathe you're
gonna have to tune into some of the
other videos but that's it for now I
really appreciate the support
if you've stumbled upon this video or
somebody shared it go ahead and
subscribe I blow or I don't know however
the hell YouTube works please subscribe
like and share if you have just enjoyed
this video I would really appreciate it
if you share it around you can see all
my websites and their places learn and
follow along but hey hopefully you learn
something now and go get some luck go
get some fatigue done go get some
challenging stuff done we'll see you
next time